holotalk and profiles in holography is
brought to you through the generous
support of the international holography
fund for more information visit their
website at holographyfund.org
[Laughter]
hi Frank hi Jonathan how are you yeah
too bad thank you so I'm glad to have
you on the show great thank you and it
has a wide listener audience okay and
let me just let the listeners know that
we're speaking to Jonathan cope and you
are in what town in England are you in
London I'm on the east coast of London
the outskirts of London okay
now you're a graduate from RCA right
that's true and maybe let me clarify
that for the listeners as well so I
don't have someone writing to me and
saying my grandfather worked for RCA
back in the 50s because RCA is actually
a company here at Royal College of Art
why don't you start off by telling the
listeners a little bit about how you got
involved with holography in the first
place
oh boy how long do we have probably not
long enough but it's about to say
um
uh I guess I've always been interested
in anything unusual
um be it uh visual or sonic
um so I guess that's kind of what drew
me in
um seeing Holograms from an early age I
was lucky enough to be born and raised
in the center of England in there called
Loughborough in leicestershire okay and
that's where a lot of the early painting
and work was done by people like Nick
Phillips at the Loughborough University
and I'm sure I would have been a case of
seeing some early exhibits probably aged
about 10 so in the mid 70s you can do
the math okay my age
um
just being really wowed by this ability
to you know view a three-dimensional
image held within a two-dimensional
plane
um and something that for me felt with
lacking in conventional art
um was that you know we live and inhabit
a three-dimensional world so in a wide
is Art have to be constrained to two
dimensions and so I guess that that
really kind of made an impact on on me
at an early age so you developed a very
intellectual Outlook toward holography
very early on in life I would say
it seems so yeah yeah I mean most kids
that are 10 years old they'll see a
hologram and go oh that's cool that's
cool but you actually had something be
some thought behind it uh I guess yeah
all the way through school I've had a
bit of an artistic inclination
um it's a good thing this interview
isn't with some of my old teachers
because it's uh probably a classic
Daydreamer and spent the whole time
staying at the school window not really
learning anything but I guess um some of
us learn in different ways
um so I've always been a very visual
oriented person so I guess that kind of
Switched me on about about Holograms did
you set up a small lab of your own or
didn't you get involved with holography
until you attended RCA
um I got involved in holography I
um let's see now so long ago it's kind
of throwing my mind back to dates must
be late 80s so around 1889 uh no way
back before that in fact well Morgan I
thought uh must be 84. I attended
um what is over here a ba in arts
ambassador of Arts I'm president I don't
know what the equivalent would be for
you guys Stateside but it was a
four-year degree course design and at
that time I had quite a strong leaning
towards computer Graphics but towards
the end of the course kind of revived my
interest in photography and managed to
find a few courses that were being run
by external sources like Richmond
holographic Studios who are quite famous
yeah that field and managed to train
with them and started to actually get
some Hands-On in holographic equipment
which I'm sure also many of the
listeners will be aware is pretty hard
and expensive to get hold of even now
what were some of the Richmond
holographics work that you got involved
with any particular pieces it was it was
not their work perceive it was the fact
that they were running courses for the
general public I so it was an easy way
to actually go in and get Hands-On
equipment in uh you know hands-only
holographical equipment for a fair price
we taught the sort of Basics and then
bringing that back into my graphic
design course to sort of show them and
is very difficult because it was all new
to them so they didn't really have any
way to rate it
um anyway to kind of appraise it so I
actually almost flunked that course
because of that they kind of just didn't
know what holography was or how it could
be used but I was lucky to get through
um that graphic design course and with a
with a person and then was very lucky to
be accepted College of Art is that
program still there at RCA unfortunately
no no
um I don't want to sound ignorant by not
knowing that already no no I think I
remember I heard that it no longer in
place yeah it's a real shame to my
knowledge it kind of died out
um about
um some of the time around 99. are there
any degreed programs in England now I
don't know of any no no no I'm not aware
of any in the states here either yeah I
just think it was one of those uh it's
going to be down to economics more than
anything I guess you know that it's
going to be a niche market there's not
that many people within the art world
who are interested in using holography
uh you know that's a really good
question I I think it's one of those
complex things with with your breakdown
into kind of public awareness
um for my short time in in the sphere
photography it seems to be one of those
things that
um goes through kind of Peaks and
troughs in terms of its Trend
um you know it's kind of really
popularized
um maybe by I don't know sci-fi or
something like that or by a big
exhibition being put out by a company
and sort of the public awareness of it
raises a while and people get excited
about it so I find that as well yeah
yeah and then that sort of seems to
Peter out again because people you know
think ultimately I guess it's still for
many people's minds constrained to that
of gimmick rather than being taken
seriously certainly that's the response
that we found within the sort of main
artistic Community I'm a kind of fine
artists kind of think it's because it's
so technical there's so many chemicals
involved in Optical equipment and it's
pretty difficult
um that does put a constraint on
creativity it's kind of hard to find
workarounds to to be creative with it
um
but yet there's so many beautiful
artistic Holograms have been created
over the years yeah well I think that
really is 10 years
of those people involved I think to get
really creative
um and and produce a work of art which
will stand alongside a kind of
conventional work of art I think is
really quite an achievement
now some of your work you've worked with
pulse telegraphy as well I know
is that you that's in the post Holograms
that I've seen I think the Jonathan Ross
collection yes it is yeah
um just the simple expedient being that
uh it's cheaper
you know you know attending the Royal
College of Art was a real dream come
true it's really fantastic but um the
bottom line is uh you start being
involved in holography and I'm sure many
of your listeners be aware it gets
pretty expensive
um you know holographic films and the
chemicals involved don't come cheap and
then certainly didn't have time and
money to spend on bringing in external
models you know using professional
people
um that way so it's easiest just to kind
of jump to the side of the plate and
press the button with myself as a
subject matter yeah
I couldn't do
and dues I wouldn't be a very
interesting subject matter but you look
good in the Holograms
that I mean I think as well is as much
to do with in the kind of the sort of
true vein of Fine Art actually it being
a self-exploratory process
um you know I was trying to depict
something of who who was where I'm
coming from where I was going to
um I mean there's a there's a piece um
called Icarus which draws on on that
ancient story yeah
I'm sorry it's gorgeous thank you uh
that was kind of the idea of trying to
get a sense of feathers you know so to
follow on the story of Icarus who didn't
listen to his father and tried to float
too close to the Sun so I guess it's all
about not listening to kind of authority
figures which is definitely uh me may I
use a picture of that on the website for
the radio broadcast yeah I I would be
very pleased and you may also do you
have a website for your work or do you
usually send people over to Jonathan
Ross collection or are you
have a music website musical instruments
that's true yeah
um that's kind of uh what I'm doing
nowadays which is very interesting but
it's a whole different world
um I still keep a lot of photographs of
my art and I've still got all the master
Holograms and many copies and you're
offering some for sale you might want to
let listeners know that as well and
where they can get them from do you
still have a page at eBay it's true yeah
I'm searching under the name of the
seller named Johnny cope uh j o n n y c
o p e hopefully would um or just under
the title of holograms because they're
not many people selling our holography
on eBay or anywhere for that matter
um it was a kind of difficult decision
for me but I've got a couple of pieces
that I always keep in my collection
because they're they're important and
dear to me but ultimately I don't have
room to display them and I think it's
better they find homes elsewhere I have
one of your Holograms oh great uh it's
one of the pulse reduction
uh yeah who is in the Hologram who is
the model for that can you remind me
Frank which which one that is uh it's uh
just a single woman that's on an eight
by ten plate okay and it's upholstery
reduction and I don't
nothing you know I don't want to say
anything badly about the woman but I
don't I can't remember anything
remarkable about it to to say that two
eyes nose a mouth okay sure
um I think from memory that was one of
the series towards the end of my time at
the Royal College of Art and that was
just really starting to experiment
um with that technique of
um reduction holography yeah that's the
only piece I've
have of a pulse reduction and only the
second one that I've ever seen in my
life okay well
um you know there are quite a lot of
accomplished artists out there using it
very successfully it's not too difficult
technique once you've created a master
hologram in this case a post laser so
you know you've actually got the
opportunity to record a living person
um which is great experience then just
simply in the transfer process putting a
large
um
uh convex lens the Glass Lens between
the master plate and the transfer plate
allows it this Optical reduction to take
place there are a number of work arounds
that have to be found to make it
actually happen yeah um but um it's
certainly an interesting process and is
equivalent then to you know kind of
photographic negative and you can make
that the final resulting image less than
life size
which is cheaper for one thing you have
an exhibit coming up at the Jonathan
Ross Gallery too is that correct
uh if I do that's nice to me oh okay I
thought I read something about that
Jonathan Ross sent me an email about uh
the program that's coming up for
holography in the modern museum and in
that email he had mentioned also that I
believe I think Amy Rush was coming up
and uh Jonathan cope okay yes that that
does remind me
um to my knowledge it's not going to be
an exhibit of of pieces it's um I've
been invited to take part in a symposium
which is going to be happening uh back
actually in my home area of
leicestershire at the De Montfort um
school okay
um and Jonathan uh you know is uh I'm
sure you're aware really very
instrumental on keeping holography kind
of out there in the art world and just
in kind of mainstream and does very a
lot of great work like this to to put on
these these talks and symposia and this
one is a very interesting one he's
approaching
um uh mainstream museums and asking them
uh you know how and where could they use
telegraphy or would they feel it
applicable to you and I guess he invited
me because I've got
um some interest and some experience in
in both spheres and I've been an art
holograph also actually after leaving
like the whole grounds where I worked
for many years
I've done six years at the British
museum so product development oh okay
yeah I remember reading about that story
so the idea is I just presented quite a
simple paper about
um what what holography could offer to
museums
to make it work for them yeah I may be
sending a hologram over for that I'm
working with students next week in
Florida okay and we're doing Holograms
of require recovered artifacts from a
sunken civil warship very great and uh
we get good results with the 30 by 40
centimeter plates and we're probably
going to send one over okay yeah
this is uh your single beam reflection
Holograms okay yeah
easiest thing to do when you have a room
full of students sure yeah yeah I still
uh yeah on some of my first programs
were dynastics as we called them then
they're beautiful if you if they're done
properly yeah absolutely and especially
on the newer emulsions where you get a
higher diffraction efficiency as well
yeah yeah excellent emotions you're
using nowadays because that was always
the problem there there's so few choices
yeah we're using the slavage emulsions
ah yeah yeah and then we have I think a
box of the BB plates
right but mostly we'll be doing 30 by 40
centimeter yeah well I wish you luck
with that thank you great what was your
biggest frustration with holography can
you think of what it was that just drove
you nuts and you just couldn't get past
it
in the creative process working with it
um I think uh putting the quite large
Financial issues aside because
um you know to to go back to the subject
we were just talking about with emotions
there were so few back then and even
less now so few producers of this very
specialized emotion
um and and it is such a specialized
process that in both nature it was very
expensive material certainly when you
start to get up into larger you know the
sort of 30 by 40 50 by 60 in case of
film yes sizes it really becomes quite
prohibitive for many people but that is
that aside I think it was just
uh the lack of color that's why I really
got interested in those those ladder
pieces that that triptych who we've
talked about one of the pieces Icarus uh
and solace
um we're really all about trying to get
to the pseudocolor technique so actually
getting some semblance of of more
natural color happening and I think
that's one of the things for me
holography by its nature is defractive
process gives a very very pure light it
can be very bright colors kind of
Prismatic rainbow colors which is very
appealing
um but I think the fact that for example
in a typical hologram portrait it's you
know mono color and it's green or yellow
yes
that's not true to life so is that
frustration which I think is being
worked right now and seeing some really
amazing work coming through from
um former Eastern block and Russia with
that Slavic material you just mentioned
I think we're getting closer and closer
to full color holography for everyone
yeah we're not that far away at least we
weren't we're not as far away as we were
even
yeah yeah so that's coming yeah I think
that you know although it's uh in a way
almost been pushed underground further
in uh you know fewer people making this
material that the people that are making
it are very specialized and they really
put a lot of research into it
um and also that some of the
Technologies is freeing up a little bit
in that
um some lasers are actually uh now we're
getting moving into solid Solid State
Technology rather than gas Blazers which
is big and clumsy and needed Cooling and
we're very very expensive now it's it's
reasonably easy to to buy these
solid-state lasers that are powerful
enough to make a reasonable size
hologram quite cheaply you know it I
think that there's sort of an idea of a
home Hollow lab takes a whole jump
close-up with with the combination of
these Technologies yeah and that's
pretty exciting I can carry a 35
milliwatt red laser around in my shirt
pocket there you go is there anything
that we didn't cover that you'd want to
cover because I am keeping my eye on the
clock and I know you said you had to run
out to pick up the little one that's
fine I'm okay for about a good 10 10 15
minutes yet oh good I really don't know
um where you'd like to to go what would
be of interest I mean
um certainly in kind of my my hologram
career this in my time working for the
Hologram companies
um did quite a long time with like
fantastic Gallery so you did some
commercial work in holography as well
what were your responsibilities doing
that
um well
um starting back in my colleges when I
was doing my four-year graphic design
course
it was unusual this timing that we were
encouraged to spend quite a lot of time
out in the industry actually as a way to
learn it wasn't just all based at a
university or a college and so I've kind
of scattered around for work and was
lucky enough to land some some work at
what was then like fantastic who were
one of the first commercial program
companies in the UK yes um and worked
their way up and ended up having quite a
large display hologram Gallery in an
area called the Trocadero in central
London and a shop and I was brought into
create
holographic products so drawing on my my
background of graphic design I could
come up with Concepts which
um allowed holography to be used as a
vehicle to actually you know provide
giftware for people the easy thing being
you know hologram of an object and then
it's just put in a frame and sold it was
kind of small art with extra Dimension
but also as well kind of trying to be
more creative with it and coming up with
um giftware that used telegraphy and in
noon in an interesting way and that was
really great opportunity and what did
you come up with
a lot of it was um one of the best
projects I I did which I really enjoyed
and was lucky enough for it to be proved
really quite successful was
um one of my other great interests is in
um ancient artifacts and ancient history
particularly as we've got such a rich
culture of that here in the UK
um and in the center of England an area
called York there was an archaeological
discovery which was found to be an early
Viking settlement which is the precursor
of what is now York and it was called
jorvik and as the jorvik center was
created for that and they had a number
of Viking artifacts which we made
Holograms of and Incorporated
Incorporated them into giftware so for
example one of the pieces was
some Viking artifacts which we made into
hologram and then I had that cup so it's
a basically a jigsaw and the idea then
that's put into a bag and uh it's sold
to children as a kind of archaeological
find that you can't tell what it is it's
in a kind of bag which is pretending to
be an archaeological finds bag with a
little tag attached to it
um with a find number in the way that an
archaeologist would tag this information
and the child has to take it home and
reassemble it to actually unlock what
one image is there and actually wow
things in 3D which is quite fun and a
number of other products as well
sell that at the bridge
of the British shop I certainly hope
they would
um that would have been ideal but
actually specifically for this quite a
large Museum which still exists in York
this York Center so they were particular
to to that that thing
you know I have a lot of towns around me
that are originally the names I imagine
were from England because York
two hours from me here in Pennsylvania
reading reading is another town right
yeah reading is about an hour and a half
so we're just filled with the English
name towns here in Pennsylvania there we
go
what's your future plans for holography
I know you haven't been doing holography
lately is that true but did you plan on
getting involved with it again or you
know have it as a memory ah it's a great
memory
um it's I try to live life without any
regrets I mean
I I need a pretty full and busy life now
I'm also a father of two children which
is great and that kind of takes up a
chunk of time and I run my own business
with this um selling of uh rare and
unusual musical instruments which is
something I really enjoy I think if I
had enough time
um which you know whoever can say that
we have enough time in our lives through
all our interests
um I I certainly would love to if I had
the space in the time and perhaps a
little bit of spare money I would love
to have a hologram Studio here again uh
in my home especially what we've said
about the the emerging technology with
solid state lasers and so on and forth
maybe it's something to think about as I
get a bit older and maybe retire
something that might resurface yeah
I was
yesterday I I actually went to a museum
yesterday and my wife and I went up to
the ticket counter and I asked for two
tickets and a woman looked at me and she
asked me senior citizen yeah
that was the first time that happened to
me in my life yesterday and I realized
it's got to happen sooner or later but I
wish it would have happened later than
yesterday right so I was asked yesterday
if I was a senior citizen well but my
hair's all turned white and everything
now you know and I just don't know yeah
but you know you still have a lot of
good years left with you I mean there
are there are labs in England where I
guess where you could rent time if you
could get contracts for Holograms right
sure yeah I mean I've really enjoyed my
time in photography I mean uh from this
early work it looked fantastic and then
directly after
um uh graduating from the Royal College
of Art I started up my own business
school pre-division
um I did a number of large-scale
holograms for for companies from the UK
and that was great and then went off to
work at Laser Holograms who ended up
being one of the largest producers of
film Holograms in Europe uh was there
for many years
um and that was all fantastic uh I think
it was only just some differences
opinions with my then business partners
led to me that business and actually
going off and working at the British
Museum and that's kind of the end of my
uh hologram career if you like and from
then it's really been put on hold
um if I had the time to get back into it
I certainly would but at this point
um my own involvement is keeping this
collection of holograms and I've got
both of my own work and other people's
but but now reluctantly I've decided to
sell a few of yeah what is the world of
holography like in England
for most General people it probably
doesn't exist it's not on their radar at
all if you ask the average person in the
street I think they would probably
scratch their head and think long and
hard and maybe make the realization that
ah yes we've got Holograms security
holograms on our banknotes currently
um or possibly those on their credit
card but otherwise I think in terms of
display holography art holography it
probably just doesn't feature uh sadly
it seems to be an uncomfortable fit with
the art world the general art community
don't really carry a great little
respect for it because there's not many
people working in it or it's difficult
to find access to for the reasons of the
equipment and the expense and so on so
forth those are horrible reasons
yeah check something it's really tough
and maybe that will start to give now um
you know if it's going to start to get
more accessible I think it needs to move
Beyond this this
um
uh being seen as a gimmick by the
general public you know it's there's not
many people that you could take into a
hologram exhibit that wouldn't go wow
you know or be amazed by a hologram but
then uh you know are they going to
remember that two weeks later or are
they going to want to see it regularly
um it's an interesting interesting point
I just I don't fully understand the
reasons behind it but for some reason
it's not really permeated through into
this kind of General culture
um for me that's probably down to the
issue of color again you know my first
time is seeing a real full color whole
event was really Beyond well you know to
see something in 3D in mono color even
the pulse portrait is really quite
standing to actually look at someone's
face in that detail in 3D but to have it
in metal color really is something else
yeah do you think that it being
associated so much with science fiction
has been a stigma to it in the art world
it's like all the Star Trek people and
everything are always talking about
Holograms are projected and you know all
this and that does that turn a number of
artists off because it's so strongly
associated with science fiction rather
it could be really onto something there
I think also as well that probably
explains for some people uh that
exposure to a real hologram Commission
of the general public might also be
conversely rather than the wow it might
be a bit of a disappointment because it
was so used to even from an early age I
mean I'm speaking from a generation
which remembers watching uh the original
Star Wars and the princess the famous
Princess Leia projection hologram
um and it's been used in so many other
things like the whole the idea of the
Holodeck and this immerses um in the
Star Trek
yeah that's a shame because there's so
many other technologies that have been
embraced yeah yeah maybe you look for
you I mean I've always been as the
opinion I'm sure this has been said by
many but holography is an application
sorry as a science waiting for an
application it's kind of still a little
bit before it's time
um so I'm hoping it's going to roll
around again and get another chance uh
to be taken more seriously okay well
we're coming up on 30 minutes Jonathan
okay so um yeah I probably need to think
about uh heading off to pick up my phone
I want to thank you for taking the time
I know you've got a very busy schedule
it's uh nice to kind of reminisce and
think back I mean it's not so long ago
I'm not so old but yeah it feels like an
age ago sometimes I'll have this up for
February 1st and all the whole listeners
will come on then it'll be archived at
profiles and holography okay which is a
site that has been funded by the
International holography fund excellent
and we thank them for that yeah I thank
you again and Jonathan it was great to
talk to you and good luck with the
conference yeah thank you I've been
thinking about it um I hold the thought
that one day I'll be involved in
photography again okay great all right
talk to you later cheers now bye